<rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title>george - Compose Articles</title><description>News, tips, and tricks from the team at Compose</description><link>http://localhost:2368/</link><generator>Ghost 0.5</generator><lastBuildDate>Fri, 13 Mar 2015 15:33:57 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://localhost:2368/author/george/rss/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><ttl>60</ttl><item><title>Elastic Deployments, now with oplog access</title><description>&lt;p&gt;We’ve just released a feature that allows all customers on our &lt;a href="http://localhost:2368/content/images/2014/12/oplog-feature_qnioxf_lp5tw6.png"&gt;Elastic Deployments&lt;/a&gt;MongoDB’s oplog plays an important role in keeping a MongoDB replica set in sync with the primary member’s state (our source of truth). As the ecosystem around MongoDB has matured, we’ve seen a proliferation of tools taking advantage of the oplog for really clever technical features.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The real-time updating web framework &lt;a href="http://meteor.com/"&gt;Meteor&lt;/a&gt; is using oplog data in its latest releases to &lt;a href="https://www.meteor.com/blog/2014/03/18/meteor-072-scaling-realtime-mongodb"&gt;synchronize changing data in MongoDB&lt;/a&gt; with connected clients without having to poll the MongoDB server for better scale and performance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://elasticsearch.org/"&gt;Elasticsearch&lt;/a&gt; can also take advantage of the oplog to keep a document index in sync by using &lt;a href="https://github.com/richardwilly98/elasticsearch-river-mongodb"&gt;MongoDB River&lt;/a&gt; to react to changes in the Mongo database. There are also a range of lower level libraries and utilities which can be customized to allow your applications to react in real-time to changes in the database.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Customers with existing Elastic Deployments can access the feature now. If you aren’t yet live MongoHQ, &lt;a href="https://www.mongohq.com/signup/"&gt;sign up now&lt;/a&gt; for immediate access.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More technical information about the feature is available on our &lt;a href="http://docs.mongohq.com/common-questions/getting-oplog-access.html"&gt;documentation site&lt;/a&gt;. If you have any questions please &lt;a href="http://docs.mongohq.com/support/new_request.html?referer="&gt;get in touch&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description><link>http://localhost:2368/elastic-deployments-now-with-oplog-access/</link><guid isPermaLink="false">b97a6330-4877-433f-8f1c-f7db61db19a4</guid><dc:creator>george</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 20 Mar 2014 17:20:26 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>